<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Codesplanations</title>
    <description>This is a \&#39;blog\&#39;, sure, but mostly a place where I can describe in detail the code I&#39;ve written provide, its origin story, lessons learned during the process, relative background information and perhaps a few anecdotes along the way.
</description>
    <link>/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 20:21:13 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 20:21:13 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sorting Music -  My First Project</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin-story&quot;&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So shortly after high school I had an HP laptop (1st mistake) that had suddenly lost its ability to charge. I didn’t have very many important documents on it, but I was bummed out that my music was locked away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an ipod at the time, and fortunately ipods retain the  music as randomized four-letter file names in hidden folders. Example shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had gotten a replacement computer (Toshiba, much better) and had transferred my music onto it and downloaded all the old applications I had. Originally I thought I was going to have to slowly rename my songs, but to my surprise, when I opened the files in itunes, all the information, artist, song name, album cover, etc. were all there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I now know this is because the files retain metadata for in the form of id3 tags. At the time, the extent of my computer ‘tricks’ were pinging in the command prompt and downloading songs off limewire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It always irked me that the files were misnamed, but I would quickly forget about it. As long as itunes made the translation when I played the song, I was willing to postpone ranaming them indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 10 years to the time of my budding computer savyness. I had recently switched from windows to my first linux distro (mint… if it matters). I was making a video and wanted to use a particular song I burned from a cd (it was Korean, so there’s no way I was gonna be able to google the name to re-download it) so I set about going one-by-one through the files to find it, as I had no itunes to translate for me. I eventually found it and made my bomb video and got a whopping 13 likes on instagram, but I didn’t want to have to do this sort of thing again. And that’s when the inspiration originiating from a divine form of laziness struck. With my newfound python and linux superpowers, I ought to be able to automate the conversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/Tclack88/blog/tree/gh-pages/assets/music-sort/unsorted_folders.png&quot; alt=&quot;unsorted fodlers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a view of the folder problem we’re dealing with&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/Tclack88/blog/tree/gh-pages/assets/music-sort/unsorted_files.png&quot; alt=&quot;unsorted files&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a look inside one of the folders to see how the music is arranged&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakdown-and-lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Breakdown and Lessons Learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the non-standard python libraries and linux tools needed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mutagen	-  pip3 install mutagen                for reading id3 tags
*avconv	-  sudo apt-get install libav-tools    for converting m4a to mp3
ffmpeg  -  sudo apt install ffmpeg 	       alternative to avconv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* avconv is deprecated at least in ubuntu 18.04, so ffmpeg is the alternative. But why the conversion? So m4a files also retain the meta data via id3 tags but the mutagen syntax doesn’t work for them, so I decided to convert. I didn’t have a preference for either format; I’m not an audio snob who cares for the slight differences in audio quality, so I elected to convert my .m4a files to .mp3. Admittedly this extra step adds time to the process (it’s almost unnoticable with ffmpeg), but also it standardizes all my audio files to one format. And this order really jives with my inner OCD-like** tendencies, so we press on. If you want to generalize this, feel free to contribute to the source code on my GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program, as of May 2019 now functions in one complete step thanks to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;os.chdir()&lt;/code&gt; which I wasn’t previously aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functional breakdown (as well as lessons learned during the process):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;collectmus()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creates a ‘tempunsorted’ directory subdirectory where everything will get sent to and an ‘oldm4a’ directory just in case the user is a snob and wishes to retain the .m4a format. No judgement.
Searches all .m4a and .mp3 files and places them in the ‘tempunsorted’ directory, to prepare them for the transmogrification (vocab nerds unite). This is tailor-made for these F## directories only, so it won’t affect the rest. Yes it’s a little over-specialized, but that was the point. You could alter the source code to work on any and all music files and subdirectories in the current directory if you’d like. This is achieved with using the re (regular expression) library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;lessons learned: use -p flag to create the parent directory if it doesn’t already exist. Saves a colossal single line in the code by calling mkdir only once (I didn’t know the power that flags held, so this was a revelation at the time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;m4a2p3()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now move right into this ‘tempunsorted’ directory and convert the heathen files. This is where the avconv linux command comes in. The .m4a extension name is retained so we have to use mv to rename them “oops I did it again.m4a” to “oops I did it again.mp3” (…what? Leave Britney alone!).
Note: I always hated underscores, so my id3 tags definitely had spaces in the name. This is reflected in the code, where I have the variable q representing the “ character. It had to be surround in triple quotes, because doubtlessly there are songs in here with ‘ characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;titlechange()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where mutagen comes in. I created an errorlist so that if anything couldn’t get converted, the user will be notified and can deal with that on a case-by-case basis. And the entire process won’t get halted because of a single rogue file. (Probably a Nickelback song)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sortbyartist()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;uses mutagen again to read the id3 tags and compiles a list of all unique artists (Sorry, if you didn’t have OCD-like tendancies** in setting your old id3 tags, you’ll just have to deal with getting “N’sync” and “Nsync” lumped as different artists)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demo--code-in-action&quot;&gt;Demo / Code in Action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is in action sorting my old music files (please no judegment on my music choices).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/Tclack88/blog/tree/gh-pages/assets/music-sort/sorting.gif&quot; alt=&quot;sorted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may notice that not everything was sorted, this is because I rather disliked having a single artist with a single song listed, so I tended to lump those together. In this particular case, the id3 tags read ‘rap/hip-hop’ which bash is interpreting as the folder ‘rap’ with the subfolder ‘hip-hop’ which doesn’t exist, so the mv won’t work. As a learning point, what single line bash command can we use to do this? Take a guess before glancing below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir rap-hip-hop &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; mv &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;.mp3 rap-hip-hop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly straight-forward simple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the breakdown. I enjoyed making it and I hope it can help anyone else to recover their old Britney and obscure korean music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Sorry to perpetuate the misuse of an actual psychoneurotic behavioral disorder, it’s just so colloquial at this point. No offense to actual sufferers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 21:45:58 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/personal/2019/05/22/music-sort.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/personal/2019/05/22/music-sort.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>from cliches import * &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hello World!</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;cliches&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello World!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excuse the stereotypical introduction, it’s tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, I have recently graduated with my B.S. in physics from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ucsb.edu&quot;&gt;University of California Santa Barbara&lt;/a&gt; where I became hopelessly overwhelmed by the amount of information there is. But it’s also filled with unfathomly gifted people among whom I will never walk. But that’s alright with me; I’m content being minimally competent with several skills rather than specializing in just a few. My perceptions have changed so much in the past decade. I thought with enough tenacity I could learn it all and I tried for &lt;a href=&quot;https://supermemo.com&quot;&gt;about 6 years&lt;/a&gt;. Chemistry, Geology, Math, Astronomy… I consumed as much as I could and regularly reviewed. It eventually became too much to keep up with, not withstanding the pressure to keep up with my degree requirements so I relented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cliche&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;two_types_of_people&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are two types of people in the world:&lt;br /&gt;
mechanics and mechanical engineers &lt;br /&gt;
What do I mean by that? I think we retain a lot more by doing rather than studying formally. The latter is certainly important, but I’ve spent so much of my life learning theory and not applying it. &lt;br /&gt;
(Perhaps it would have been a more productive 6 years if I had turned to DIY projects more often than textbooks.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;little-more-about-me&quot;&gt;Little more about me&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve gained and lost many hobbies and micro-hobbies over the years, but the ones that seem to be staying are: Rock climbing, piano and coding. I can speak French decently well and my Spanish is alright. I’m intrigued by all things arcane: morse code, elian script, unit conversions(there are 4 pecks in a bushel), interesting vocab words, etc. I’m pedantic to a fault and I hate driving, especially because that’s when random questions come to mind and I can’t (safely/legally) google them. This is starting to get a little personal, so let’s switch gears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;purpose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;While&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I intend to use this outlet to speak about the code I’ve written — particularly inspiration for its conception, lessons learned during the process and some relevant/interesting background information. I’m not not really an expert at anything and won’t feign to be a guru, but there may be some room for tutorials here, or at the very least my interpretation of grotesque, overly technical subjects as I come to understand them during my own learning process. Hopefully this will be a productive use of webspace. I don’t care for personal blogs, but such material may slip in from time to time, so I apologize in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I wish to leave the world a better condition than when I arrived. As such, I intend to do what I can to reduce global emissions be it through contributions to renewable energy technologies or by reducing wasted energy by working on energy efficiency projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough of this, let’s start digging in to the details.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 14:45:58 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/personal/2019/05/22/hello-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/personal/2019/05/22/hello-world.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
